suppose we have a function f and we draw
the graph y as a function of X like this
now imagine we have an input x equals a
and we want to know what the instant
rate of change of the function at x
equals a is how can we figure this out
one way is to take a separate Point
labeled X and draw the secant line
connecting the two points the slope of
this secant line is the average rate of
change of f between X and A and it's
given by the slope formula f of x minus
F of a over x minus a now here's the
trick we can compute this average rate
of change for any value X except for x
equals a because that would require us
to divide by zero so what we do is we
actually take a limiting value of the
slopes of the secant lines as X
approaches a and this gives us the
instant rate of change of F at x equals
a so we can Define f Prime of a to be
this limit as X approaches a of f of x
minus F of a over x minus a provided the
limit exists we call this the derivative
of F at a and it measures the slope of
the tangent line or the instant rate of
change of F at a